[Music]
welcome back to reality asserts itself
i'm paul jay
on the real news network we're
continuing our series of interviews with
john kiriakou the former cia
officer and in the last episode we left
on a cliffhanger so if you didn't watch
the last episode we better go back and
watch in fact you probably should watch
all the preceding episodes because we're
just going to pick it up thanks for
joining us again thanks for having me
all right so what happened next well as
part of my job
with the senate foreign relations
committee like everybody else on the
committee staff
i had lunch on a regular basis with
foreign diplomats
and during those lunches we would talk
about whatever happened to be in the
news
israeli elections developments in turkey
yemen is collapsing whatever happened to
be interesting
and we would just give each other our
views on these uh
news events so i was having lunch
with a japanese diplomat at his
invitation at a restaurant on capitol
hill
and toward the end of the conversation
he said to me so what's next for you
and i said well i'm actually thinking of
resigning i promised senator kerry i'd
give him two years it's been two and a
half
i miss working for myself i think i'm
gonna i'm gonna move on
to do what i wanted to go back into
consulting again
and he got very excited and he said no
don't do that
i can give you money if you give me
information
and i said do you have any idea how many
times i've made that pitch
shame on you for even saying something
like that i'm going to have to report
this
well i went directly from the lunch to
the office of the senate security
officer
and i said i was just pitched by a
foreign intelligence officer
so he asked me to write him a memo and
he would send the memo to the fbi so i
wrote a very detailed memo
about the lunch and it went to the fbi
and then two days later two fbi
agents came up to the senate security
office to interview me
and they said what we want you to do is
to call him back
invite him to lunch and try to get him
to tell you exactly what information
he's looking for
and how much money he's willing to pay
for it and we're going to have two
agents at the next table
to listen in on the conversation i said
terrific
so i called him i invited him to lunch
and we went to the lunch and we had a
another great conversation and he told
me what he was interested in
i should add the the fbi didn't show up
to sit at the next table right before
that lunch they called and said
just go ahead and do it and write us
another memo so who's setting you up the
fbi or the cia
well i thought that i was helping out
the fbi by helping them identify a
foreign intelligence
officer so i did this a second time
and a third time and a fourth time and i
might have even had a fifth lunch with
him
finally he told me that are you thinking
this is a setup no
no i thought this was a
counterintelligence investigation
so finally he tells me i'm being
transferred to uh
i said okay good luck nice to meet you
nice to know you
and i never saw him again it wasn't
until a year later
that we learned that there was no
japanese
intelligence officer there was no
japanese diplomat he was an fbi agent
and what they were trying to do was to
set me up on a real
espionage charge not one of the
espionage charges that they ended up
putting on me all of which were dropped
i should add
they knew that their espionage case
against me was
was weak to non-existent i hadn't
committed espionage
in fact one of the espionage charges i'm
going to interrupt myself here
one of the espionage charges was based
on the fact that i had leaked
top secret compartmented information
about a cia program to the new york
times do you know what that information
was
that the cia had a program to capture
or kill al qaeda members
come on i got an espionage charge for
that
the other two espionage charges were
based on the fact that i had given a
former cia colleague's business card
he's no longer in the cia and he was
never
undercover i had given this business
card to two reporters
one at abc and one at the new york times
so i got three espionage charges wait a
second if you're not undercover
there's lots of ci agents officers that
are known and
they get talked about in fact when we
raised this in court
uh my attorney told the judge your honor
this this man was never undercover
and all my client did was to to pass his
business card which he's handing out to
everybody
to these two reporters and the judge
said i find that
very hard to believe so she turns to the
prosecutors and she says is that true
and the prosecutor says well your honor
mr kiriakou really should have been more
careful
and and she turns to my attorneys and
says i'll entertain a motion to dismiss
those charges
they were all eventually dropped but
they knew the fbi knew that these
that these charges and the espionage
case against me was very weak
so what they wanted to do was to catch
me actually
committing espionage and so they
sent in this pretend japanese diplomat
okay you didn't fall for it but they
continue to target
you anyway right but see all this time i
didn't know
that i was being targeted when i had
lunch with a japanese diplomat
this was 2011. this was the spring of
2011.
i wasn't arrested until 2012 and what
really did me in
was in january of 2012 i got a call
from the fbi hi this is so-and-so with
the fbi field office
in washington do you remember that case
you helped us out with
about a year ago i said sure about the
foreign diplomat and he said yeah
i said yeah sure i remember he said well
we've got a similar case and we really
need your help
can you come down here i said sure in
fact i said
anything for the fbi well come on down
on uh
on thursday i said terrific so i go down
on thursday
and meet with these two fbi agents in a
secure vault
vaulted conference room and we're an
hour into this meeting before i realized
wait a minute this is this case is
against me
i had no idea but i should have known
because
another thing happened that same week
the previous week
my mother's sister died in western
pennsylvania
and so i rented a car and i went to the
funeral what turned out i also had
a hearing in ohio at family court in
ohio on
child support so
i rented this car i went to my aunt's
funeral and then
from the funeral in pennsylvania i drove
to warren ohio
and i checked into a motel to wait for
the
the hearing on monday afternoon
so monday morning i didn't have anything
to do i got up and i thought
i'm going to go look at my grandparents
old house i haven't seen it in
15 years i'm going to drive through the
neighborhood and see what what it looks
like
so i drive up to the house and i'm going
like two miles an hour and i noticed
there's a toyota behind me
so i waved an apology and i sort of
pulled over the side of the road and
they don't want to pass
he didn't want to pass and i thought
well that's odd so i drive
up to the intersection and i make this
great big u-turn in the intersection
well this guy makes a great big u-turn
as well and i thought
all right it's either he's a carjacker
or he's a private eye that my ex-wife
hired to follow me
so i know the neighborhood well i cut
through the neighborhood
using what i would have called a
surveillance detection route
i already knew that i was being followed
and i drive to the cemetery where my
grandparents are buried
so i i stop the car near their graves i
get out this guy
passes me and parks about a hundred feet
away and turns around and he's just
watching me
yeah they want you to know right it was
pretty clear
so i called my wife and i said
this is gonna sound crazy but i'm under
surveillance
and she agreed with me that it was
probably my ex-wife having hired a
private eye
to catch me doing what i had no idea but
then
from there wouldn't be so obvious right
from there i drove to
uh the packard museum remember the car
the packard from the 40s and 50s well it
was made in that town warren ohio
and there's a packard music hall and
next to it is the packard museum
so i drove into the parking lot of the
packard museum and i made a u-turn there
he did the same i waited until the light
was red and then i
sped through the red light and he got
caught up in traffic
and then i just sort of went in my way
back to the uh to the
motel so i thought well some local yokel
private eye just got too close didn't
know what to do
because i was driving erratically and i
didn't think about it well
it was after this meeting with the fbi
four days later that i realized
it was the fbi they had followed me all
the way from virginia
they probably thought i was running to
canada or something
because their call had tipped me off i
didn't know
but but i realized that next thursday in
that meeting that i'm in deep trouble
in fact at the end of the of the meeting
they said
well you should know that as we speak
we're executing a search warrant
on your home and i said am i under
arrest
and he said not yet and i said well i
want to talk to my attorney
triggered by what according to them this
meeting with this japanese
phony japanese diplomat they decided
they couldn't charge me with that
which they couldn't because i hadn't
done anything wrong and they went ahead
and charged me with three counts of
espionage related to the
saying that the cia was capturing
al-qaeda
leaders uh and the the two business
cards so that i got three espionage
charges there
they added a charge of making a false
statement to the cia's publications
review board
which was absurd that was in the process
of of writing my book they said that i
made a false statement
i don't even recall what the false
statement was supposed to have been but
i remember sitting in the conference
room with
my lawyers and they said so what exactly
was the
was the false statement and i said i i
don't know i don't know what
this is supposed to be i was supposed to
have lied to them somehow
anyway they also charged me with one
count of violating the intelligence
identities
uh intelligence identities protection
act of 1982 in the business card no it
was different because that guy was never
undercover
uh i had gotten a call in
2008 so this is four years earlier i had
gotten a call from a reporter
who was writing a book on the rendition
program
and he wanted to know if i knew anybody
that i could introduce him to
that he could interview for the book i
said i don't know anybody i didn't have
anything to do with rendition i really
never
met any of those guys so he said well
what about the guy
in your book that you mentioned running
into
at the airport in in pakistan
and i said yeah i can't remember his
name and he said
i think his first name is john i said oh
right that's john doe or john smith
i said i don't know where he is he's
probably retired and living somewhere in
northern virginia
that was a felony and i served two years
in prison for that conversation
that's the one you actually had to plead
to yes
so they tried hard to get me and when i
say hard i mean
they tried to get me 45 years so that's
the
the the short of the to jump to the
chase
you were facing all these espionage
charges right so you plea to this one
my investigator developed information
indicating that the reporter did not get
that name from me
he got it from a disgruntled former cia
officer in bethesda maryland
so why didn't you fight it well we went
to the prosecutors to fight it and the
prosecutor said first of all you can't
prove that we withheld the information
you can't prove that we ever had the
information
secondly we'll drop that charge we'll
drop that iipa charge
but we're going to go after you on the
three espionage charges but why they're
so ridiculous the three espionage
charges why didn't you fight them
because this is the eastern district of
virginia it's called the espionage court
and nobody ever wins in the eastern
district of virginia this is why i told
ed snowden
when he first went public don't come
home because you won't get a fair trial
your jury's going to be made up of fbi
agents
military officers cia officers you're
never going to get a fair hearing here
never so for me it ended up being an
economic question
can my family live without me for two
years
basically on the kindness of strangers
and family members
and the answer was yes but could they
live without me for 20
which is what i realistically could have
expected if i had been convicted of the
espionage charges no they couldn't have
made it for 20.
so i cut my losses and i took a plea
it's extortion
but this is what the justice department
does what they do is they
heap charges on you knowing that they're
going to drop
all of them but one if you take a plea
because what you're eventually going to
do is you're going to be
so beaten down you're going to spend
every cent you have
and every cent you've been able to
borrow from friends or family members
you're going to spend your pension
unless they take it away from you like
they did in my case
and you're going to still have to take
your pension away from you yeah i lost
my federal pension
i've got nothing i'm going to have to
work till the day i die
there's nothing i can do about it so
what they do is they heap on these
charges
knowing that eventually you're going to
give up and you're going to take a plea
that's why according to propublica that
actually studied this
the feds have a 98.2 percent conviction
rate
i said in a speech right before i went
to prison saddam hussein won 98
of his last presidential election and we
said the fix was in the justice
department wins 98.2 percent of their
cases and we say they're geniuses
i say there's something wrong with the
system now this was all designed
to send a message in the cia do not
if you're one of us you don't even poke
around at all
and it sounds the more you tell a story
it's it's almost sounds like it's less
about
that you went public on torture which
i'm sure pissed them off at the time
sure
but the fact that you keep poking right
and and number two to shut you up
this has not shut you up quite the
opposite no quite the opposite in fact
i said again in a speech before i went
to prison if they thought this would
shut me up
they don't know me at all because now
i've devoted my life
to fighting them thanks for joining us
happy to be here and thank you for
joining us on reality asserts itself
on the real news network and i'm sure
john's going to be back on the real news
not too distant future
[Music]
you